<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Image Processing | Archana Swaminathan</title>
    <link>https://archana1998.github.io/tag/image-processing/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://archana1998.github.io/tag/image-processing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Image Processing</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Archana Swaminathan, 2020 ©</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 18:40:47 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://archana1998.github.io/images/icon_hu616effff6bc497e1f3ccd40e4a444d66_14554_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Image Processing</title>
      <link>https://archana1998.github.io/tag/image-processing/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compressive Sensing and Denoising of Images using the Ramanujan Fourier Transform</title>
      <link>https://archana1998.github.io/project/compressive-sensing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 18:40:47 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://archana1998.github.io/project/compressive-sensing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ramanujan Sums were first proposed by Srinivasan Ramanujan in 1918, and have become exceedingly popular in the fields of signal processing,time-frequency analysis and shape recognition. The sums are by nature, orthogonal. This results in them offering excellent conservation of energy, which is a property shared by Fourier Transform as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have used Matrix Multiplication to obtain the Ramanujan Basis, for our computation. The Ramanujan Sums are defined as n&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; powers of q&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;primitive roots of unity, which can be computed using this simple formula:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$c_{q}(n)=\mu\left(\frac{q}{g c d(q, n)}\right) \frac{\varphi(q)}{\varphi\left(\frac{q}{g c d(q, n)}\right)}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where $q=\prod_{i} q_{i}^{a_{i}}$,(q&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; is prime). Then, $\varphi(q)=q \prod_{i}\left(1-\frac{1}{q i}\right)$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\mu(n)$ is the Mobius function, which is equal to 0 if n contains a square number, 1 if n = 1 and (-1)*k if n is a product of k distinct prime numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ramanujan matrix can be defined as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$A(q, j)=\frac{1}{\varphi(q) M} c_{q}(\bmod (j-1, q)+1)$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2-D forward Ramanujan Sum Transform is given as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$Y(p, q)=\frac{1}{\varphi(p) \varphi(q)} \frac{1}{M N} \sum_{m=1}^{M} \sum_{n=1}^{N} x(m, n) C_{p}(m) C_{q}(n)$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which in matrix terms can be defined as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$Y=A * A^{\top}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and the inverse 2D Ramanujan transform in matrix terms is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$X=A^{-1} Y\left(A^{-1}\right)^{\top}$$&lt;/p&gt;





  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-original-transformed-and-inversed-image&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://archana1998.github.io/project/compressive-sensing/montage1_hu3f8e044785174c9754427187ccca8f30_16041_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;673&#34; height=&#34;184&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
    Original, Transformed and Inversed Image
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;compressive-sensing&#34;&gt;Compressive Sensing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principle behind the use of compressive sensing as a signal processing technique, is that most test signals are not actually completely comprised of noise, but most have a great degree of redundancy in them. Sparse representation of signals in a particular domain signifies that most of the signal coefficients are either zero or close to zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compressive measurements, which are a weighed linear combination of signal samples, are first taken in a basis that is different from the sparse basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;algorithm&#34;&gt;Algorithm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use the generated Ramanujan Basis to do the sparse reconstruction. First, the sparse signal is obtained by multiplyingthe Ramanujan Basis A with the flattened image vector (here we are using the Cameraman Image that has been resized to 50 * 50).
Our Ramanujan Basis has dimensions of 2500 * 2500.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$Z=A^{*} x$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where Z is the sparse representation of the cameraman image, and x is the flattened image vector of the original image.
We next create a random measurement matrix of dimension m*n, where we keep m = 5000 and n = 2500. This measurement matrix (Phi) is then multiplied by the sparse signal z.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$Y=P h i * Z$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then use Orthogonal Matching Pursuit Algorithm, which aims to approximately find the most accurate  projections of data in multiple dimensions on to the span of a redundant or overcomplete dictionary. Here, the overcomplete dictionary we use is the Ramanujan Basis A.
The orthogonal matching pursuit algorithm is then applied onto the signal Y, and we have considered 1700 iterations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plot of the original sparse representation and the OMP representation is given below:&lt;/p&gt;





  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-plot-of-original-sparse-representation-blue-and-omp-representation-red&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://archana1998.github.io/project/compressive-sensing/plot1_hudbf82b9e3e6b647977479df89ebf2cb6_10556_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;628&#34; height=&#34;333&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
    Plot of original sparse representation (blue) and OMP representation (red)
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image is then reconstructed by taking the inverse of the Ramanujan Basis, and multiplying it with the OMP sparse representation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$R e c  =A^{-1} * x w s r$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where xwsr is the OMP representation, and Rec is the reconstructed image signal. This is then resized to obtain the final image, which has been compared with the original image below:&lt;/p&gt;





  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-original-and-final-image&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://archana1998.github.io/project/compressive-sensing/orgvsfinal_hu69f64e62c985d6a5e0fb9a9c8fbbb991_25782_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;317&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
    Original and Final image
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We compare and evaluate the performance of the Compressive Sensing Algorithm by using PSNR, SSIM and MSE image evaluation metrics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PSNR: Peak Signal to Noise Ratio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SSIM: Structural Similarity Index&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MSE: Mean Square Error&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally, high values of PSNR, SSIM(max=1) and MSE show favourable performance of the reconstruction algorithm.The results obtained for this approach are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PSNR = 23.1362&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SSIM = 0.6265&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MSE = 315.8316&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;image-denoising&#34;&gt;Image Denoising&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image denoising is commonly analysed and solved as an inverse problem. A method of doing this is to decompose the image signal in a sparse way, over a dictionary that is overcomplete. We use the Ramanujan Dictionary here to do the denoising, which is trained with three images using the K-SVD algorithm, based on Orthogonal Matching Pursuit (OMP).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;k-svd-algorithm&#34;&gt;K-SVD Algorithm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The K-SVD algorithm is a type of K-means clustering, which has been generalized. The k-
means clustering is also considered a method of doing representation of sparse signals. This
implies solving the equation below, to find the best code to represent the signal data {y&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;} from i=1 to M&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\min &lt;em&gt;{D, X}\left{|Y-D X|&lt;/em&gt;{F}^{2}\right}, \text { subject to } \forall i,\left|x_{i}\right|_{0}=1$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;F here is the Frobenius norm. The K-SVD algorithm is similar to the K-means in terms of the process of construction, but differs in the sense of the relaxation of the sparsity term in the constraint. This helps achieve a linear combination of the dictionary atoms. The relaxation is that the number of entries that are not zero in each column can be greater than 1, but less than a defined number T&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the objective function hence becomes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\min &lt;em&gt;{D, X}\left{|Y-D X|&lt;/em&gt;{F}^{2}\right} \text { , subject to } \forall i,\left|x_{i}\right|_{0} \leq T_{0}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the algorithm, the dictionary D is first fixed, and the aim is to find the perfect coefficient matrix X. To find this, a pursuit method that does the approximation of the optimal X is used. OMP was chosen as the suitable method to calculate the coefficients of the matrix here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implementation-and-results&#34;&gt;Implementation and Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the implementation for training the dictionary  nd the sparse data representation, the
parameters for the training are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patch Size = 15&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Percentage of Overlap = 0.5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sparsity Threshold = 6&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Error Tolerance = 11.5
Three images, Boat, Lena and Barbara were used for the dictionary training. Patches were made
of these images and stacked. The number of iterations was the size of the stacked images that
formed the training data. In this case, the number was 2883. The dictionary and sparse data
representation were trained using the K-SVD algorithm and saved, the training process took
approximately 5.5 hours on an Intel i5 6 th gen processor, with a Nvidia 940mx GPU (personal laptop, using MATLAB R2019a).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;





  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-original-and-reconstructed-boat-image&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://archana1998.github.io/project/compressive-sensing/reconmontage1_hu1cc507d436712babecbb0e0103bd6f3d_16355_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;205&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
    Original and Reconstructed Boat image
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We added Gaussian Noise to a Lena Image and denoised it using the trained dictionary.&lt;/p&gt;





  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-original-noisy-and-denoised-lena-image&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://archana1998.github.io/project/compressive-sensing/denoised_huf16ae9dc124035bdd7e9ad8e397ffe59_15436_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;154&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
    Original, Noisy and Denoised Lena image
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MSE for noisy image = 68.0747&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MSE for denoised image = 55.2772&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PSNR for noisy image = 29.8009&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PSNR for denoised image = 29.9672&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ramanujan Transform is a powerful transform and basis dictionary that can be used for sparse representation of an image. It can be trained efficiently and reconstructs images in a
better way as compared to using DCT dictionary. For compressive sensing algorithm, the training time of the Ramanujan dictionary is more compared to the DCT dictionary training time, but it is more efficient in reconstruction. It is also good at denoising images, and is efficiently trained using the K-SVD algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
